Guide to The Karl and Erna Kordesch Papers 1906-2011
Special Collections Archives Research Center, The Valley Library
Karl and Erna Kordesch Papers
1906-2011
Oregon State University Libraries Special Collections University Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: special.collections@oregonstate.edu Web: http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/specialcollections
MSS Kordesch
Kordesch, K. (Karl), 1922-
14 linear feet 36 boxes 11 gigabytes Personal and professional correspondence, research materials, financial records, scientific publications, corporate materials, immigration and employment documentation, photographs, and bibliographic records.
Karl Kordesch (1922-2011) was a distinguished Austrian-American chemist widely recognized for his contributions to battery and fuel cell research and technology. Kordesch was jointly responsible for the invention of the alkaline primary dry cell battery, significant developments in fuel cells, and the successful creation and operation of hybrid vehicles. During his career, Kordesch was responsible for more than 100 hundred patents as well as numerous papers, articles, and books on the subject of electrochemistry, effectively revolutionized the battery industry, and pioneered electric/fuel cell vehicles. The Karl and Erna Kordesch papers contain records of much of Karl's research and publishing efforts as well as biographical records, photos, and ephemera documenting the Kordeschs' life in Nazi-occupied Austria and the United States.
Materials in fair to very good condition.
Archived electronic records are viewable onsite upon appointment.
Biographical Note
Karl Kordesch is recognized as a pioneer of battery and fuel cell technology responsible for vastly extending the utility of non-petroleum electrical energy sources through the invention and refinement of electrochemical devices and processes. Through his invention of the alkaline primary battery cell, work with rechargeable batteries, and development of fuel cell/battery hybrid vehicle systems, Karl Kordesch contributed greatly to the reduction of energy waste and the global use of compact, portable energy sources.
Karl was born in Vienna, Austria on March 18, 1922 and Erna Bӧhm was born six months later, on September 8, 1922. After graduating from high school in 1940 Karl began studying at the University of Vienna. In 1941, Karl was conscripted into the German military where he served until the end of World War II in 1945. In 1946, he and Erna were married and he returned to his studies at the University of Vienna. Karl graduated in 1948 with his doctorate in chemistry and worked as a University Assistant at the University of Vienna. In 1953, Karl accepted a position with the U.S. Army Signal Corps through Operation Paperclip, an Office of Strategic Services program designed to supplement American scientific research with Axis personnel in exchange for U.S. citizenship and other benefits. Karl and Erna moved their family to New Jersey where he served with the Signal Corps until 1955 when he joined the Union Carbide Corporation. There, he developed the manganese dioxide-zinc primary cell which became the leading consumer battery worldwide. He also worked extensively with fuel cells, contributing new technology to the Apollo space missions and developing a hydrogen fuel cell/battery system capable of powering his personal vehicle, an Austin A40, efficiently for more than three years.
In 1977, Karl left his position at Union Carbide to return to Austria with Erna where he worked as director of the Institute for Inorganic Chemistry at the Graz University of Technology. There, he continued his research into rechargeable batteries, fuel cells, and more efficient methods for powering vehicles. In 1986, Kordesch founded Battery Technologies Inc., a company responsible for the manufacture of rechargeable batteries sold under Rayovac. Karl also formed the Kordesch Associates, Inc. consulting firm in 1988. In 1997, Kordesch accepted a position as vice-president of Apollo Energy Systems where he oversaw fuel cell research for use in consumer vehicles. The Kordeschs moved to Eugene, Oregon they lived until Karl's death in 2011. Karl Kordesch was survived by his wife, Erna Kordesch, and his four children.
During his lifetime, Kordesch produced more than one hundred patents, hundreds of articles and papers, and numerous books. He was an active participant in the scientific community, frequently attending and presenting at meetings and symposia, collaborating with colleagues around the globe, and acting as a leader in his field through service as the Secretary General of the International Society for Electrochemisty. His achievements have been recognized through his receipt of the prestigious William Exner Medal, the Vittorio de Nora Gold Medal Award, and the Erwin Schrödinger Prize, among others.
Timeline for Karl and Erna Kordesch
1922 Kordesch is born on March 18, 1922 in Vienna, Austria. Erna Bӧhm is born on September 8, 1922 in Reichenau, Austria.
1940 Kordesch begins his first year at the University of Vienna.
1941 Kordesch is conscripted into the German Armed Forces, interrupting his studies at the University of Vienna.
1944 Kordesch is wounded while serving in Russia.
1945 Kordesch is released from military service at the end of World War II, having attained the rank of Lieutenant Battery Leader.
1946 Kordesch and Erna Bӧhm are married on June 22, 1946. Kordesch returns to the University of Vienna to complete his studies.
1947 Johanna Kordesch, Karl and Erna's first child, is born on February 24, 1947 in Vienna, Austria.
1948 Kordesch receives his doctorate in chemistry from the University of Vienna. Kordesch works as a University Assistant at the University of Vienna until 1953.
1949 The second Kordesch child, Albert, is born on August 15, 1949 in Vienna, Austria. Kordesch accepts a part-time consulting position for Wiener Isolierrohr, Batterie, und Metallwarenfabrik, a battery manufacturer located in Vienna while continuing to work at the University of Vienna.
1953 As a part of Operation Paperclip, Karl Kordesch is invited to join the U.S. Signal Corps. Kordesch and his family move to the United States and Karl begins work as scientific staff member of the U.S. Signal Corps at Fort Monmouth, New Jersey.
1954 Catherine Kordesch, the third Kordesch child, is born on January 24, 1954.
1955 Kordesch accepts a position as Battery Group Leader at the Union Carbide Corporation Research Laboratory in Parma, Ohio.
1956 The fourth Kordesch child, Martin, is born on July 22, 1956.
1957 Kordesch and two colleagues file for a patent of the alkaline dry cell battery which would ultimately become the Energizer D-cell.
1962 Kordesch is appointed group leader of the Fuel Cell Section of the Corporate Development Department at Union Carbide.
1967 Kordesch receives the Wilhelm Exner Medal from the Austrian Association of Small and Middle-Sized Enterprises. Kordesch constructs a hybrid electric motorcycle using a hydrazine fuel cell.
1969 Kordesch returns to the Consumer Products Division of Union Carbide as a Senior Research Associate.
1970 Kordesch retrofits an Austin A40 sedan to run on a hydrogen fuel cell, making it the first practical hydrogen-fueled car ever produced. This vehicle served as his primary means of transportation for the following three years.
1973 Kordesch is appointed Union Carbide Research Fellow.
1977 Kordesch takes a position as full professor at the Graz University of Technology and director of the Institute for Inorganic Chemistry.
1981 Kordesch begins a five-year term as Secretary General of the International Society for Electrochemistry.
1985 Kordesch is appointed Dean of the Science and Technology Faculty at the Graz University of Technology, a position in which he serves until 1987.
1986 Kordesch is awarded the Vittoria de Nora Gold Medal for outstanding achievement by the U.S. Electrochemical Society. Battery Technologies, Inc. is founded by Karl Kordesch and Wayne Hartford.
1988 Kordesch Associates Inc. is founded by Karl as an electrochemistry consulting firm.
1990 Kordesch receives the Erwin Schrödinger Prize from the Austrian Academy of Sciences.
1991 Kordesch receives the Frank M. Booth Prize of the Royal Society of Great Britain.
1992 Kordesch retires from the Graz University of Technology and the Institute of Inorganic Chemistry. Kordesch is awarded the Auer V. Welsbach Medal.
1996 Kordesch and Günter Simader publish Fuel Cells and Their Applications.
1997 Kordesch becomes vice-president of Apollo Energy Systems where he was responsible for overseeing further development of the company's line of fuel cells.
2009 Kordesch is recognized by the American Chemical Society for fifty years of service.
2011 Kordesch dies on January 12, 2011 in Eugene, Oregon.
Content Description
The Karl and Erna Kordesch Papers are comprised of approximately ten linear feet of content documenting Karl's professional career from the late 1940s until his death in 2011 and an additional four linear feet of assorted personal records from both Karl and Erna. The collection contains an extensive record of Karl Kordesch's career including patent records, research notes, documentation of various business ventures, and correspondence, as well as materials regarding Karl's participation in the United States' post-World War II Operation Paperclip. The Karl and Erna Kordesch Papers also include an extensive collection of photographs documenting life in World War II-era Austria and the mid-20th century American Midwest. In addition to its physical holdings, the collection also contains more than 10 gigabytes of electronic documents including correspondence, publications, and digital photographs relating to Karl Kordesch's research.
Arrangement
The Karl and Erna Kordesch Papers are arranged by medium, subject, and chronology.
Restrictions on Access
Permission to examine the Karl and Erna Kordesch Papers will be granted to qualified researchers upon completion of an "Application for Use" form, and contingent upon the researcher's agreement to abide by the rules and policies governing collection use. See the Use of Collections page for more information.
Custodial History
Ownership of all materials in the Karl and Erna Kordesch Papers were transferred to Erna Kordesch upon Karl Kordesch's death. Erna Kordesch donated all materials to OSU Libraries Special Collection on April 22, 2011. Additional materials created by Catherine Kordesch were donated by on December 28, 2011.
Acquisition Information
14 linear feet and 7.5 gigabytes of materials were accessioned from Erna Kordesch by OSU Libraries Special Collections on April 22, 2011.
3.5 gigabytes of electronic records were accessioned from Catherine Kordesch by OSU Libraries Special Collections on December 28, 2011.
Future Additions
No future additions are anticipated.
Selected Publications by Karl Kordesch
Kordesch, Karl. Batteries, Vol. 1: Manganese Dioxide. New York: Marcel Dekker, 1974.
Kordesch, Karl. Batteries, Vol. 2: Lead-Acid Batteries and Electric Vehicles. New York: Marcel Dekker, 1977.
Kordesch, Karl. Brennstoffbatterien. Vienna; New York: Springer, 1984.
Kordesch, Karl and Simader, Günter. Einsatz der Brennstoffzellen-Technologie für die Dezentrale Energienutzung Zweite Endbreicht einer Studie der EVA und TU Graz im Auftrag der Steirischen Elektrizität- und Wasserkraft-AG (STEWAG). Vienna: EVA, 1998.
Kordesch, Karl and Simader, Günter. Fuel Cells and their Applications. Weinheim; New York: VCH, 1996.
Kordesch, Karl and Kornfeil, Friedrich. Method and Device for Testing Nickel-Cadmium Batteries. Ft. Belvoir, VA: Ft. Belvoir Defense Technical Information Center, 1954.
Kordesch, Karl. Versuch zur Aufarbeitung von Gelatine-Hydrolysaten nach den Methoden der Hochvakuumdestillation, Cu-Salz Trennung und Chromatographie.. Vienna: University of Vienna, 1948.
Additional Reference Guides
Related Materials
Separated Materials
Subjects
The following Library of Congress Authorities headings suggest topics, individuals or organizations interspersed through the collection.
Personal Names
Kordesch, Erna.; Hacker, Viktor.; Kordesch, Erna.; Simader, Günter.
Organizational Names
Battery Technologies, Inc.; Operation Paperclip (U.S.); Technische Universität Graz.; Union Carbide Corporation.; United States. Army. Signal Corps.
Subject Terms
Battery industry--United States.; Electric automobiles.; Fuel cells.; Hybrid electric vehicles.; Scientists--United States--Recruiting.; Storage batteries.
Compact discs.; Film negatives.; Photograph albums.; Floppy disks.; Photographic prints.; Slides.
Science; Technology; Transportation; Women; Electronic Records; Photographs
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Scientific Research Materials, 1950-2011; undated; 1; 24 boxes
  Contains research notes, reports, publications, correspondence, visual aids, and patent information pertaining to battery, fuel cell, and electric/hybrid vehicle research. Includes materials created by Karl Kordesch and others involved in the development of non-petroleum based energy sources.
  - Battery Research, 1950-2010; undated; 1; 6 boxes
    - Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, 1950-1996 (Box 1.001)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1950-1991 (Folder 1.1)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1992-1996 (Folder 1.2)
    - Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, 1997-2010; undated (Box 1.002)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1997-2010 (Folder 2.1)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, undated (Folder 2.2)
    - Non-Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, 1956-2005 (Box 1.003)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1956-1993 (Folder 3.1)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1994-1995 (Folder 3.2)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1996-1997 (Folder 3.3)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1998-2005 (Folder 3.4)
    - Non-Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, undated (Box 1.004)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, undated (Folder 4.1)
    - Assorted Informational and Promotional Materials (Box 1.005)
      - Assorted informational and promotional materials, undated (Folder 5.1)
      - Battery Technologies, Inc. informational and promotional materials, undated (Folder 5.2)
    - Assorted Scientific Journals, 2000-2010 (Box 1.006)
  - Fuel Cell Research, 1959-2007; undated; 2; 7 boxes
    - Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, 1959-2007 (Box 1.007)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1959-1969 (Folder 7.1)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1970-1989 (Folder 7.2)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1993-2000 (Folder 7.3)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 2001-2007 (Folder 7.4)
    - Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, undated (Box 1.008)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, undated (Folder 8.1)
    - Kordesch Reports to Union Carbide, 1960-1969 (Box 1.009)
      - Quarterly progress reports, 1960-1962 (Folder 9.1)
      - Monthly reports, 1963-1969 (Folder 9.2)
    - Non-Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, 1958-2002 (Box 1.010)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1958-1970 (Folder 10.1)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1993-1999 (Folder 10.2)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 2000-2002 (Folder 10.3)
    - Non-Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, 1967-2007; undated (Box 1.011)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 2003-2007 (Folder 11.1)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, undated (Folder 11.2)
      - Reports from G. R. Drengler, 1967-1969 (Folder 11.3)
    - Assorted Informational and Promotional Materials (Box 1.012)
      - Assorted informational and promotional materials, undated (Folder 12.1)
    - Assorted Scientific Journals, 1963-2006 (Box 1.013)
  - Electric/Hybrid Vehicle Research, 1964-2010; undated; 3; 5 boxes
    - Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, 1970-2007; undated (Box 1.014)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1970-2007 (Folder 14.1)
      - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, undated (Folder 14.2)
    - Non-Kordesch Research Notes, Reports, and Publications, 1964-2007; undated (Box 1.015)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 1964-1983 (Folder 15.1)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, 2000-2007 (Folder 15.2)
      - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, undated (Folder 15.3)
    - Electric Auto Corporation/Apollo Energy Systems Internal Documents, 2000-2005 (Box 1.016)
      - Electric Auto Corporation/Apollo Energy Systems internal documents, 2000-2005 (Folder 16.1)
    - Assorted Informational and Promotional Materials (Box 1.017)
      - Assorted informational and promotional materials, undated (Folder 17.1)
      - Materials re: The Electric Vehicle Association of Ohio, undated (Folder 17.2)
    - Assorted Scientific Journals, 1992-2010 (Box 1.018)
  - Correspondence, 1967-2011; undated; 4; 1 box
    - Correspondence, 1967-2011; undated (Box 1.019)
      - Correspondence re: Battery research, 1987-2010; undated (Folder 19.1)
      - Correspondence re: Fuel cell research, 1967-2010 (Folder 19.2)
      - Correspondence re: Electric/hybrid vehicle research, 1967-2007; undated (Folder 19.3)
      - Assorted correspondence, 2001-2011 (Folder 19.4)
  - Diagrams, Overhead Slides, and Photographs, undated; 5; 1 box
    - Assorted Diagrams, Overhead Transparencies, and Photographs (Box 1.020)
      - Assorted visual aids (paper), undated (Folder 20.1)
      - Assorted visual aids (transparencies), undated (Folder 20.2)
      - Assorted visual aids (photographs), undated (Folder 20.3)
  - Patents and Documentation of Invention, undated; 6; 1 box
    - Patents and Documentation of Invention (Box 1.021)
      - Batteries, undated (Folder 21.1)
      - Fuel cells, undated (Folder 21.2)
      - Assorted inventions, undated (Folder 21.3)
  - Dissertations, 1983-2001; 7; 1 box
    - Dissertations: Cifrain, Donne, Ghaemi, Hacker, 1995-2001 (Box 1.022)
      - Cifrain, Martin. Thin Carbon-based Electrodes for Alkaline Fuel Cells with Liquid Electrolyte. [Bound], 2001 (Folder 22.1)
      - Donne, S.W. High Performance Chemically and Physically Modified Manganese Dioxide. [Bound], 1996 (Folder 22.2)
      - Ghaemi, Mehdi. Herstellung elektroaktiver Schichten für die Anwendung in wiederaufladbaren bipoilaren Bruanstein-Zink-Batterien. [1 bound, 1 unbound], 1995 (Folder 22.3)
      - Hacker, Viktor. Technologische Übergangsstrategien zur Regenerativen Energiewirtschaft: Der Einsatz von Biomasse in Kombination mit der Brennstoffzelle. [Unbound], 1998 (Folder 22.4)
    - Dissertations: Haynes, Koscher, Weingartner, 1983, 1988; undated (Box 1.023)
      - Haynes, A. “Summary of Dissertation Work.” [Bound], 1988 (Folder 23.1)
      - Koscher, Gerold. Carbon-based Electrodes for Alkaline Fuel Cell Systems with Various Fuels. [2 partial copies, 1 bound and 1 unbound], undated (Folder 23.2)
      - Weingartner, August. Berechnungen zur Holzvergasung in der Wirbelschicht. [Unbound], 1983 (Folder 23.3)
    - Dissertations: Weißenbacher, 1996; undated (Box 1.024)
      - Weißenbacher, Manfred. Das wiederaufladbare alkalische Zink/Braunstein-System: Neue Wege zur Berbessergun des Zyklenlebens. [2 bound copies], 1996 (Folder 24.1)
- "Box Zero", 2; 1 box
  Materials specially collected and housed by Karl Kordesch. Karl designated this group of materials as "Box Zero", indicating that they were of particular scientific and biographical value. Series includes assorted notes, reports, publications, patent information, and correspondence.
  - Contents of "Box Zero", undated (Box 2.001)
    - Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, undated (Folder 1.1)
    - Non-Kordesch research notes, reports, and publications, undated (Folder 1.2)
    - Assorted patents and related documents, undated (Folder 1.3)
    - Assorted documents re: WIF, undated (Folder 1.4)
      Documents regarding a World War II-era German flashlight manufacturer.
    - Assorted correspondence, undated (Folder 1.5)
- Biographical Materials and Photographs, 1906-2010; undated; 3; 10 boxes
  Biographical materials relating to members of the Bӧhm, Colnago, Kordesch and Marko families including personal documents and photographs.
  - Karl Kordesch, undated; 1; 3 boxes
    - Biographical Materials re: Karl Kordesch (Box 3.001)
      - Identification and citizenship, undated (Folder 1.1)
      - Military service and Operation Paperclip, undated (Folder 1.2)
      - Educational records, undated (Folder 1.3)
      - Financial records, undated (Folder 1.4)
      - Legal records, undated (Folder 1.5)
      - Medical records, undated (Folder 1.6)
      - Travel records, undated (Folder 1.7)
    - Biographical Materials re: Karl Kordesch (Box 3.002)
      - Assorted correspondence, undated (Folder 2.1)
      - Newspaper and magazine clippings, undated (Folder 2.2)
      - Assorted professional contacts, undated (Folder 2.3)
      - Résumés and biographies, undated (Folder 2.4)
    - Biographical Materials re: Karl Kordesch (Box 3.003)
      - Assorted keepsakes, undated (Folder 3.1)
  - Erna Kordesch, undated; 2; 1 box
    - Biographical Materials re: Erna Kordesch (Box 3.004)
      - Identification and citizenship, undated (Folder 4.1)
      - Educational records, undated (Folder 4.2)
      - Newspaper clippings, undated (Folder 4.3)
      - Personal histories, undated (Folder 4.4)
        Birth stories of the four Kordesch children and other events dictated by Erna Kordesch and recorded by Catherine Kordesch.
      - Assorted correspondence, undated (Folder 4.5)
      - Assorted keepsakes, undated (Folder 4.6)
  - Kordesch Family, undated; 3; 1 box
    - Biographical Materials re: The Kordesch Family (Box 3.005)
      - Materials re: Kordesch genealogy, undated (Folder 5.1)
      - Assorted Kordesch family postcards, undated (Folder 5.2)
      - Assorted Kordesch family keepsakes, undated (Folder 5.3)
  - Bӧhm/Colnago Family, undated; 4; 1 box
    Materials relating to members of the maternal (Colnago) and paternal (Bӧhm) sides of Erna Kordesch's family.
    - Biographical Materials re: The Bӧhm/Colnago Family (Box 3.006)
      - Materials re: Bӧhm/Colnago genealogy, undated (Folder 6.1)
      - Assorted Bӧhm Family Correspondence, undated (Folder 6.2)
      - Correspondence from Erna Kordesch to Bianca Bӧhm, undated (Folder 6.3)
      - Assorted correspondence to Bianca Bӧhm, undated (Folder 6.4)
      - Assorted correspondence to Erna Colnago, undated (Folder 6.5)
      - Assorted Bӧhm family keepsakes, undated (Folder 6.6)
  - Photographs, 1900s-2000s; undated; 5; 4 boxes
    - Photographs, 1900s-2000s; undated (Box 3.007)
      - Photographs of Karl Kordesch, 1940s (Folder 7.1)
      - Photographs of Karl Kordesch, 1950s (Folder 7.2)
      - Photographs of Karl Kordesch, 1970s (Folder 7.3)
      - Photographs of Karl Kordesch, 1990s (Folder 7.4)
      - Photographs of Karl Kordesch, 2000s (Folder 7.5)
      - Photographs of Erna Kordesch, 1930s (Folder 7.6)
      - Photographs of Erna Kordesch, 1940s (Folder 7.7)
      - Photographs of Erna Kordesch, 1950s (Folder 7.8)
      - Photographs of Erna Kordesch, 1990s (Folder 7.9)
      - Photographs of Erna Kordesch, 2000s (Folder 7.10)
      - Photographs of Karl and Erna Kordesch, 1940s (Folder 7.11)